Finding Aid for Michigan Interscholastic Press Association records, 1928-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Interscholastic Press Association records 1928-1972
Michigan Interscholastic Press Association.
85293 Bh 2
Organization of advisors of school publications, sponsored by the journalism department at the University of Michigan, 1921-1972. Annual reports and minutes of executive committee; files relating to conventions, conferences and workshops; correspondence and miscellaneous subject files; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
2 linear feet
The record group was received from the University of Michigan Department of Communication (donor no. 1674 ) in 1982.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Interscholastic Press Association was started in 1921 at the University of Michigan under the guidance of Professor John L. Brumm of the Department of Journalism. Sponsored by the University of Michigan, its purpose was to improve the teaching and practice of journalism in the state of Michigan. Membership to MIPA was open to advisors of school publications in Michigan at a high school, junior high, junior college or college level. High school advisors comprised the majority of Association members. A director, appointed by the University of Michigan Journalism department, and an executive committee, comprised of eight advisors who were elected at the annual convention, appointed regional directors and planned the annual convention.
The first annual conference was held in 1922 at the University of Michigan; it was sponsored by Sigma Delta Chi, the national Journalism fraternity. In 1927 the MIPA took over from Sigma Delta Chi. The annual convention as well as regional conferences and summer workshops grew to be central focus of the MIPA.
There were no annual conferences from 1943 to 1948, but in 1949 the conference grew from what had been a one day affair to a three day event. Professor John Field took over from Professor Brumm in 1951, assuming the motivating force as director. Field was instrumental in the growth of MIPA, organizing regional conferences in all parts of the state. Haven Hill, a two-day conference for advisors was started in 1954. Field remained director until 1971 when Professor Tom Rood took over the responsibility. In 1972 the sponsorship of MIPA changed and it was moved to Central Michigan University.
The conferences and workshops sponsored by the MIPA which took place on the University of Michigan campus were held at the Michigan Union until 1949. From 1949 to 1968 they were held at Rackham and from 1969 to 1971 in the Michigan League.
The Michigan Interscholastic Press Association record group provides documentation of its administration and programmatic activities with high school newspapers and journalism programs around the state. The records are organized into five series: Executive Committee Minutes; Conventions, Conferences and Workshops; Correspondence; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Journalists--Michigan.; Michigan Interscholastic Press Association.; University of Michigan--Congresses.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; Journalism, High school--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Education--Michigan.; Classrooms.; Clothing and dress--1951-1960.; Clothing and dress--1961-1970.; Education.; Journalism.; Michigan Interscholastic Press Association.; Newspaper carriers.; Newspapers--Michigan.; Printing industry.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Executive Committee Minutes of the MIPA
  The Executive Committee Minutes series consists primarily of annual reports and minutes with some correspondence.
  - Annual reports; minutes 1951, 1953, 1954-1964 (Box 1)
- Conventions, Conferences and Workshops
  This series documents the various conventions, conferences and workshops of the MIPA. The Annual Convention, held in the spring of every year, was the focus of much of the activity of the MIPA. Registration lists and programs are the most important items in the series. The advisors' conference was held at Haven Hill Lodge every year in the fall, and various correspondence and reports document this event. The other activities in this series summer workshops, Upper Peninsula Conferences and regional conferences are documented primarily by programs.
  - Annual Convention
    - Registration and membership lists 1951-1969 (Box 1)
    - Programs 1933-1972 (Box 1)
  - Haven Hill Advisors' Conference
    - Reports 1958-1972 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, registration lists and correspondence 1953-1971, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Summer Workshops
    - 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - Upper Peninsula Conferences
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Regional Conferences
    - Programs (Scattered years) (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The correspondence series comprises the largest part of the collection. Primarily covering the years from 1950 to 1971, this series consists of correspondence between John Field and various advisors throughout Michigan. There is some correspondence relating to high school curriculum and problems concerning the teaching of journalism. A good deal of the correspondence relates to Field's communication with various public figures regarding speaking at the Annual Convention. The time and energy John Field expended for the MIPA is particularly evident in this series.
  - 1928-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1950/1951-1954/1955, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1955/1956-1970/1971, 15 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The most interesting file in the Miscellaneous series is the committee report of the San Francisco Curriculum Survey and the correspondence which the report generated.
  - Critiques by MIPA of High School Papers (Box 2)
  - San Francisco Curriculum Survey (Box 2)
  - Scholarships and Awards (Box 2)
  - Student papers and Miscellaneous MIPA Publications (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The photographs in this series are of participants in, and activities of, workshops for high school yearbook editors and advisors.
  - Undated, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
  - 1955 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1956 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1957 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1958 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1959 Workshop (Box 2)
  - Unlabeled 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - 1960 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1961 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1962 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1963 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - 1966 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1967 Workshop (Box 2)
  - 1969 Workshop (Black Workshop) (Box 2)
  - Students (Box 2)